<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thoughts on Rajath Ramakrishna</title>
    <link>/tags/thoughts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Thoughts on Rajath Ramakrishna</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Copyright notice</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 17:44:42 -0700</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/thoughts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On Analysis Paralysis</title>
      <link>/posts/on-analysis-paralysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2021 17:44:42 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/on-analysis-paralysis/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have often gotten stuck in analysis paralysis mode where I constantly look for the right way to solve a problem and end up spending way too much time on it than actually solving the problem. A lot of times what happens is the activity of searching for the right way to do something itself takes so much time and energy that I&amp;rsquo;d develop an aversion to the actual activity. Or I&amp;rsquo;d not feel the same level of enthusiasm with which I started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A recent example for this was when I was thinking about the right way to journal. I&amp;rsquo;ve been journaling on and off the past few years and I&amp;rsquo;ve also changed my note-taking apps/services a few times. These note-taking apps have also influenced the way I journal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I currently use &lt;a href=&#34;https://orgmode.org&#34;&gt;org-mode&lt;/a&gt; to manage my tasks, events, journal, notes, thoughts, etc. Given that I wanted to journal in org-more, I started searching for the best ways to go about it - to &amp;ldquo;streamline the process&amp;rdquo;, so to speak. Like, what would the headings be? Should I follow a template? Can I use a text expander for the template? Should I add tags for each heading in that template? I was even looking up the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.reddit.com/r/Journaling&#34;&gt;/r/journaling&lt;/a&gt; subreddit to get some ideas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But after spending some time on this, it just hit me - I should worry more about content than workflows. So, I just went ahead and freestyled it by putting in vague yet meaningful enough headings for each journal entry that either captures the task/event/feeling. And then I added tags to capture how I&amp;rsquo;m feeling. This took a lot of stress away from me and helped me focus on journaling instead of building a workflow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is just one example out of several where I spent too much time trying to find the right way to do something before actually doing it. What I realized from the above experience was to identify what is important to me. In the journaling example, what&amp;rsquo;s important is the content - writing down what I think, how I feel, rationalizing my thoughts when I&amp;rsquo;m anxious, etc. Everything else is secondary. As long as I make it extremely easy to accomplish this, I shouldn&amp;rsquo;t care about workflows. Because, workflows develop organically based on usage.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
