<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>clickbait on Rajath Ramakrishna</title>
    <link>/tags/clickbait/</link>
    <description>Recent content in clickbait on Rajath Ramakrishna</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Copyright notice</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 22:43:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/clickbait/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Clickbaits are here to stay</title>
      <link>/posts/clickbaits-are-here-to-stay/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 22:43:00 -0800</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/clickbaits-are-here-to-stay/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;More than a decade ago I came across BuzzFeed articles like &amp;ldquo;10 things you didn&amp;rsquo;t know about the Illuminati, number 7 will surprise you&amp;rdquo; for the first time. At the time, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even know they were called clickbait. This reminded me of the tabloids I saw near checkout lines in grocery stores. Every time I&amp;rsquo;d see one of those magazines, I used to think, &amp;ldquo;This is beyond ridiculous. Who reads this stuff?&amp;rdquo;. In my mind, I used to categorize tabloids as the lowest form of &amp;ldquo;news&amp;rdquo; and just a desperate attempt to get peoples&amp;rsquo; attention to buy those magazines, and in my opinion that&amp;rsquo;s still the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I started seeing more and more clickbaits online, I started becoming infuriated because now they were everywhere. I was seeing the equivalent of tabloid headlines in most of the websites I used to visit and it felt like there was no escaping them. I initially thought only sites like BuzzFeed and similar ones would be so desperate for attention and clicks, and real news sites wouldn&amp;rsquo;t need clickbaits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was wrong. I started seeing them even on websites like HackerNews or AndroidPolice. It was annoying me so much that I didn&amp;rsquo;t click those links on purpose, even though I knew it had information that I was looking for. It was my way of &amp;ldquo;vote with your clicks&amp;rdquo;. And then, it was all over YouTube too. The channels I subscribe to - Red Delta Project, Veritasium, etc. that have nothing to do with gossip or sensational news, but instead make educational content were also filled with titles that were very clickbait-y.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t like it, and I was hoping this was just a fad that would pass. I thought it would be one of those things where companies would jump on just to be part of whatever trend was going on and then drop it when it&amp;rsquo;s no longer &amp;ldquo;cool&amp;rdquo;. But at the back of my mind, I was thinking that clickbaits are only growing because they work. People click such links and clicks is what a service primarily measures (among other things) the popularity of its article.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently saw a video on Veritasium titled &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=S2xHZPH5Sng&#34;&gt;Clickbait Is Unreasonably Effective&lt;/a&gt;. This hit home with me. If people tend to click on clickbait articles, then there &lt;em&gt;will&lt;/em&gt; be more clickbait articles. This is one thing if a blog contains a bunch of such articles. But if a serivce like YouTube takes uploaded videos and ranks them, and happens to find clickbait-y videos perform better, it&amp;rsquo;ll just rank those videos higher. And if I&amp;rsquo;m a YouTube content creator, and I want to stay in the game, I&amp;rsquo;d have to play the same game. As much as I hate clickbait, I&amp;rsquo;d still have to add a clickbait title, a clickbait thumbnail and a clickbait caption in the thumbnail. And not to forget a corny facial expression on the thumbnail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I saw in the above video did put things into perspective as to why clickbait even exists and why everybody seems to be using it more and more. I still cringe when I see such titles. What scares me even more is, a lot of times any title I try to come up with for a blog post that I write, I start feeling like it&amp;rsquo;s clickbait-y. I spend more time thinking about how to not make the title sound very clickbait-y. Or how to make the title sound as least clickbait-y as possible. Sometimes I fail. But I still try.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess what I&amp;rsquo;m trying to say are two things:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whether anybody likes it or not, I think clickbaits will continue ot exist and thrive as long as clicks (or click-through rate) is used as one of the dominant metrics. That&amp;rsquo;s just the world we live in now.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I try my best to come up with titles that are not clickbait-sounding. I&amp;rsquo;d rather want the reader to not be interested to read my blogpost after looking at the headline than cringe hard at the headline.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
