<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>2019 on Rajath Ramakrishna</title>
    <link>/tags/2019/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 2019 on Rajath Ramakrishna</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>© Copyright notice</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/2019/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>2019 in Review</title>
      <link>/posts/2019-year-in-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019-year-in-review/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Another year done, and like always time flies by quicker and quicker every year. 2019 has been quite eventful in a few aspects and I took some time to reflect on how things went. This time I categorized my activities and personal growth into 3 sections - things I did more of, things I did less of, things I explored. Let&amp;rsquo;s begin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;things-i-did-more-of&#34;&gt;Things I did more of&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;running&#34;&gt;Running&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was faster (compared to last year) in almost all my races in 2019. I also participated in more races and set a few PRs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;stats&#34;&gt;Stats&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in for Autism 10K - 53m 33s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mother&amp;rsquo;s Day Half - 1h 57m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Big Run 5K (trail run) - 29m 1s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Evergreen Half - 1h 53m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Craft Classic Half - 1h 49m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Iron Horse Half - 1h 42m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fly 5K - 25m 46s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snohomish 10K - 51m 51s&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Snohomish River Run Full - 3h 56m&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started off with the 10K in April with no training and I&amp;rsquo;m happy to see that my time only improved from then on. There was a time when I was running half marathons every couple of weeks and it got a little exhausting. But it feels great to look back and see all the races I&amp;rsquo;ve done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;marathon&#34;&gt;Marathon&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The full marathon gets a special mention because the training was fun and the race, even more so. In 2018, I did my first full marathon and the training was quite brutal - mostly because I didn&amp;rsquo;t know what to expect. And, I got first hand experience of what mile 18 feels like in a full marathon. But in 2019, I knew how the training would be, I knew how to prep and how to recover, when to push myself and when to take it easy. I used &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.halhigdon.com/training-programs/marathon-training/intermediate-1-marathon&#34;&gt;Hal Higdon&amp;rsquo;s Intermediate 1 training plan&lt;/a&gt; and made my own modifications to it. Overall, I improved and set a PR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;traveling&#34;&gt;Traveling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did some traveling in 2019 with a few road trips - one in Oregon, couple in Washington, and few hikes around Seattle. I also visited Los Angeles. The most amazing and memorable one was the 4-day Inca Trail hike to Machu Picchu which was a birthday gift from my wife. Highly recommend going there and doing the 4-day hike, it&amp;rsquo;s totally worth it. Also, a shout out to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.alpacaexpeditions.com&#34;&gt;Alpaca Expeditions&lt;/a&gt; for their awesome crew that helped us with the hike, food, camps, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;things-i-did-less-of&#34;&gt;Things I did less of&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;reading&#34;&gt;Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I fell off on the reading habit and ended up reading only about 14 books (compared to 24 in 2018). This is something I want to get back into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;working-out&#34;&gt;Working out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hardly worked out last year and thanks to my training for marathon, I just didn&amp;rsquo;t have the time or energy to work out at all. When I wasn&amp;rsquo;t training for my marathon, I was just plain lazy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;bouldering&#34;&gt;Bouldering&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This fell off also because of my marathon training. I used to be regular and climb twice a week. But it just wasn&amp;rsquo;t feasible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;things-i-explored-aka-side-quests&#34;&gt;Things I explored (aka Side Quests)&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;snowboarding&#34;&gt;Snowboarding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I picked up snowboarding in early 2019, thanks to my wife. I fell in love with it. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t super interested in winter activities before, but after giving snowboarding a try I was always looking forward to driving to a nearby mountain and keep getting better at snowboarding. I&amp;rsquo;ll be doing more of that this year for sure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;self-hosting&#34;&gt;Self Hosting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stumbled upon self hosting recently and it looked very appealing to me. The fact that I could just use Raspberry Pis to self host few things is what made me more inclined towards trying it out and playing with it. I see privacy concerns with storing my data on Google servers or with any other big corporations. I&amp;rsquo;d rather be in charge of my own data. So, I decided to slowly move things off of cloud services that I&amp;rsquo;m currently using and host my own data. I already set up a private cloud server and it&amp;rsquo;s working like a charm. I got to learn lot of new technologies and it&amp;rsquo;s been fun tinkering with Raspberry Pis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;learning-new-things&#34;&gt;Learning new things&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my journey of learning to self host, I stumbled upon Docker, Traefik, Ansible, Prometheus, Grafana and I&amp;rsquo;ve been keen on learning these new technologies. I&amp;rsquo;ve also learnt a lot about networking, DNS, dynamic DNS, VPN, etc. I&amp;rsquo;ve spent many hours playing around with these, failing, learning and redoing a lot of the setup. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun exercise which will continue this year as I get better at hosting a robust system with everything I need.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;indie-web&#34;&gt;Indie Web&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I stopped using social media platforms like Facebook, Twitter, Instagram few years ago. I knew about what Mastodon was in principle about a year ago, but never really got around to exploring it much. But towards the end of 2019, I checked out few instances in Mastodon and started exploring. I really liked the idea of instances that are built on certain set of principles and people adhering to it, and federating with other instances. I&amp;rsquo;ve only started with Mastodon, but I&amp;rsquo;ll soon be exploring Pixelfed, Pleroma and the likes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;lessons-learned&#34;&gt;Lessons Learned&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;you-cant-do-everything&#34;&gt;You can&amp;rsquo;t do &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s how my brain works. I find something interesting, I want to learn more about it. But I also don&amp;rsquo;t want to give up on all the things I&amp;rsquo;m already doing. I fall short on some of the things (because it&amp;rsquo;s not realistic to master everything, given the limited number of hours in a day). I get disappointed that I&amp;rsquo;m not doing enough. I&amp;rsquo;ve been doing this for years, even though I know that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense. What I should constantly remind myself is that I can&amp;rsquo;t do (or master) &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;. I should identify core areas where I want to grow and then focus all my energy on that. I should still explore things, and some of them may grow into something bigger and more important for my personal growth. But I must always acknowledge the fact that there is only limited amount of time and I must use it wisely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;less-consumption-more-creation&#34;&gt;Less consumption, more creation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t do more of is work on side projects, or create more. Even though, I don&amp;rsquo;t use social media, I still check a lot of blogs and stuff myself with information. It&amp;rsquo;s exhausting. Every time I have couple of minutes free on my hand, I check my phone and try to read a blog post. I have to practice to sit still, not touch my phone and not look at any screen. I used to meditate regularly and it definitely helps with being mindful about what we do. This is something I really want to do this year.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
